# **ANDRÉ FELIPE MENEZES**

B.Sc., M.Sc.



**D** 0000-0002-3320-9834

**J** +353 083 141 8439

andrmenezes.github.io



# SUMMARY

I am a Statistician with experience in statistical modeling, more precisely in scRNA-seq data analysis, Bayesian dynamic models, and quantile regression models. I am interested in researching about analysis and development of statistical models to Biology phenomena, computational implementation of statistical models, and development and application of Bayesian dynamic models.

## WORK EXPERIENCE

#### Statistician and Data Scientist

#### Murabei

**J**une 2020 - July 2022

São Paulo, SP, Brazil

Data analysis and modeling for national and international companies, including the following challenges:

- Forecast models for scrap price.
- Forecast massive number of hierarchical time series.
- Forecast availability of returnable containers in production plants.
- Optimization decision model for minimum-cost flow problem.
- Credit risk score with focus on small companies.
- Predict models for control quality processes.
- Pricing models for credit recovery.

#### Intern

#### **Bradesco Bank**

August 2018 - February 2019

Curitiba, PR, Brazil

- Extract, Transform and Load (ETL) large databases for credit risk studies.
- Creation of automated process using SAS and R for preview risk evaluation.
- Credit Intelligence Academy: short course with focus on credit risk areas of modeling, strategy, and MIS.

# **PROJECTS**

## Statistical Methods for scRNA-seq Data Modeling CNPq/Unicamp

**February 2019 - April 2021** 

Campinas, SP, Brazil

- I studied techniques used for data analysis in scRNA-seq, which include (i) methods for pre-processing raw data, (ii) data processing of counting matrix and (iii) statistical methods for data analysis.
- Real data analysis of cells from bronchoalveolar lavage fluid (BALF) tissue from patients with COVID-19 was performed to characterize groups of cells and comparing the genes expression level of the patients.

# **EDUCATION**

## Ph.D. in Data Science **Maynooth University**

Sep 2022 - Ongoing

## M.Sc. in Statistics **State University of Campinas**

- **Mar 2019 May 2021**
- Thesis theme: Statistical Methods for scRNA-seg Data Modeling

#### B.Sc. in Statistics

#### State University of Maringá

- Feb 2014 Feb 2019
- Developed projects:
  - Bias correction methods of maximum likelihood estimators.
  - · Probability distributions with bounded support on (0,1).
  - A review of Geostatistics methodology.

# **STRENGTHS**

Hard-working Self-taught Collaboration Statistical Modeling scRNA-seq Time Series Bayesian Inference C++ python cloud tools docker microservices PLEX.

# LANGUAGES

- Portuguese (Native)
- English (Advanced)

# Methods of Bias Correction of Maximum Likelihood Estimators

#### CNPq/UEM

- **i** July 2017 July 2018
- Maringá, PR, Brazil
- I studied three approaches to obtain bias-corrected maximum likelihood estimates for the parameters of any probability distribution.
- I also introduced the mle.tools R package which can be used to computes the expected/observed Fisher information and the bias corrected estimates for the parameters of any probability distribution.

# **PUBLICATIONS**

# Software

- Menezes, A. F. B., & Pinheiro, E. G. (2022). pybats-detection: A python package for outlier and structural changes detection in time series analysis. python package available at: https://github.com/Murabei-OpenSource-Codes/pybats-detection.
- Menezes, A. F. B. (2021). RBATS: Bayesian Dynamic Models. R package available at: https://github.com/AndrMenezes/RBATS.
- Menezes, A. F. B., & Mazucheli, J. (2021). Unitquantreg: Parametric quantile regression models for bounded data. R package available at: https://github.com/AndrMenezes/unitquantreg. Retrieved from https://andrmenezes.github.io/unitquantreg

### Journal Articles

- Menezes, A. F. B., Bourguignon, M., & Mazucheli, J. (2022). Complementary beta regression model for fitting bounded data. *Journal of Statistical Theory and Practice*, 16(22). doi:10.1007/s42519-022-0025
- Mazucheli, J., Alves, B., Menezes, A. F. B., & Leiva, V. (2022). An overview on parametric quantile regression models and their computational implementation with applications to biomedical problems including COVID-19 data. Computer Methods and Programs in Biomedicine, 221, 106816. doi:10.1016/j.cmpb.2022.106816
- Menezes, A. F. B., Mazucheli, J., & Bourguignon, M. (2021). A
  parametric quantile regression approach for modelling zero-orone inflated double bounded data. *Biometrical Journal*, 63, 841–
  858. doi:10.1002/bimj.202000126
- Menezes, A. F. B., Mazucheli, J., & Chakraborty, S. (2021). A collection of parametric modal regression models for bounded data. Journal of Biopharmaceutical Statistics, 31(4), 490–506. doi:10. 1080/10543406.2021.1918141
- Menezes, A. F. B., Mazucheli, J., Oliveira, R. P., & Chakraborty., S. (2021). Improved maximum likelihood estimation of the parameters of the gamma-uniform distribution with bias-corrections. *Communications in Statistics Simulation and Computation*, 1–13. doi:10. 1080/03610918.2021.1951760
- Mazucheli, J., Menezes, A. F. B., Alqallaf, F., & Ghitany, M. E. (2021). Bias-corrected maximum likelihood estimators of the parameters of the unit-Weibull distribution. Austrian Journal of Statistics, 50(3), 41–53. doi:10.17713/ajs.v50i3.1023

# **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

2020	Undergraduate Tutor
	Descriptive Statistics
	State University of Campinas
2019	Undergraduate Tutor
	Database for statistics
	State University of Campinas
2016	Undergraduate Tutor
	Statistics for engineering
	State University of Maringá
2015	Undergraduate Tutor
	Probability and Statistics
	State University of Maringá

## **SHORT COURSES**

2018	Joint Models in Biostatistics
0047	State University of Maringá, 6h
2017	Elements of Computational Statistics
0047	University of São Paulo, 6h
2016	Graphical Optimization in the R
	Environment
0047	State University of Maringá, 9h
2016	Introduction to R
0047	UDEMY, 15h
2016	Big Data and data visualization in R
0047	Graduate Program of Biostatistics, 6h
2016	My first R package
	Graduate Program of Biostatistics, 2h
2016	Production of dynamic reports using
	knitr and Rmarkdown
	Graduate Program of Biostatistics, 2h
2015	Aplied geostatistics
	Federal Technological University of
	Paraná, 8h
2015	Survival analysis
256-w	State University of Maringá, 8h
2015	Demystifying LETEX
	State University of Maringá, 8h
2014	Inductive inference: A genuinely
	Bayesian view
	State University of Maringá, 6h
2014	Introduction to R
	State University of Maringá, 16h
2014	Introduction to SAS, LATEX, and Sweave
	State University of Maringá, 48h
2013	Excel: Basic resources
	SENAC, 21h
COM	TEDENICE TAI VO

# **CONFERENCE TALKS**

- Mazucheli, J., Leiva, V., Alves, B., & Menezes, A. F. B. (2021). A new quantile regression for modeling bounded data under a unit Birnbaum-Saunders distribution with applications in medicine and politics. Symmetry, 13(4), 1–21. doi:10.3390/sym13040682
- Menezes, A. F. B., & Mazucheli, J. (2020). Improved maximum likelihood estimators for the parameters of the Johnson SB distribution. *Communications in Statistics Simulation and Computation*, 49(6), 1511–1526. doi:10.1080/03610918.2018.1498892
- Menezes, A. F. B., Mazucheli, J., Cardoso, J., & Chakraborty, S. (2020). The Transmuted Half-Normal distribution with application to precipitation data. *Pesquisa Operacional*, 40(e216792), 1–30. doi:0.1590/0101-7438.2020.040.00216792
- Mazucheli, J., Menezes, A. F. B., Dey, S., & Nadarajah, S. (2020).
   Improved parameter estimation of the Chaudhry and Ahmad distribution with climate applications. *Chilean Journal of Statistics*, 11(2), 137–150.
- Mazucheli, J., Menezes, A. F. B., Fernandes, L. B., Oliveira, R. P., & Ghitany, M. E. (2020). The unit-weibull distribution as an alternative to the kumaraswamy distribution for the modeling of quantiles conditional on covariates. *Journal of Applied Statistics*, 47(6), 954–974. doi:10.1080/02664763.2019.1657813
- Mazucheli, J., Bapat, S. R., & Menezes, A. F. B. (2020). A new one-parameter unit-Lindley distribution. *Chilean Journal of Statistics*, 11(1), 53–67.
- Mazucheli, J., Bertoli, W., Oliveira, R. P., & Menezes, A. F. B. (2020). On the discrete quasi xgamma distribution. *Methodology and Computing in Applied Probability*, 22, 747–775. doi:10.1007/s11009-019-09731-7
- Menezes, A. F. B., & Furriel, W. O. (2019). Beta and simplex regression models in the analysis of the municipal human development index 2010. *Revista Brasileira de Biometria*, *37*(3), 394–408. doi:10.28951/rbb.v37i3.408
- Dey, S., Menezes, A. F. B., & Mazucheli, J. (2019). Comparison of estimation methods for unit-Gamma distribution. *Journal of Data Science*, 17(4), 768–801. doi:10.6339/JDS.201910\_17(4).0009
- Ghitany, M. E., Mazucheli, J., **Menezes, A. F. B.**, & Alqallaf, F. (2019). The unit-inverse Gaussian distribution: A new alternative to two-parameter distributions on the unit interval. *Communications in Statistics Theory and Methods*, 48(14), 3423–3438. doi:10.1080/03610926.2018.1476717
- Mazucheli, J., & Menezes, A. F. B. (2019). L-Moments and maximum likelihood estimation for the Complementary Beta distribution with applications on temperature extremes. *Journal of Data Science*, 17(2), 391–406. doi:10.6339/JDS.201904\_17(2).0009
- Mazucheli, J., Menezes, A. F. B., & Dey, S. (2019a). Bias-corrected maximum likelihood estimators of the parameters of the inverse Weibull distribution. *Communications in Statistics - Simulation and Computation*, 48(7), 2046–2055. doi:10.1080/03610918.2018. 1433838
- Mazucheli, J., Menezes, A. F. B., & Dey, S. (2019b). Unit-Gompertz distribution with applications. *Statistica*, 79(1), 25–43. doi:10. 6092/issn.1973-2201/8497
- Mazucheli, J., & Menezes, A. F. B. and Chakraborty, S. (2019). On the one parameter unit-Lindley distribution and its associated regression model for proportion data. *Journal of Applied Statistics*, 46(4), 700–714. doi:10.1080/02664763.2018.1511774
- Oliveira, R. P., Menezes, A. F. B., Mazucheli, J., & Achcar, J. A. (2019). Mixture and nonmixture cure fraction models assuming discrete lifetimes: Application to a pelvic sarcoma dataset. *Bio-*

- 2017 The use of discrete cure fraction model in the analysis of oncological outcomes in the treatment of pelvic sarcomas. I Statistical Modeling Meeting, Maringá.
- 2017 Regression models for proportions: Beta and Simplex with applications to MHDI
   2010. I Statistical Modeling Meeting, Maringá.
- 2017 Monte Carlo study of multiple comparisons corrections in t-test. 5th Workshop on Probabilistic and Statistical Methods, Federal University of São Carlos, São Carlos.
- 2016 Likelihood ratio, Wald, and Score statistics in small samples for Beta distribution. I Biostatistics Workshop, Maringá.

- metrical Journal, 61(4), 813-826. doi:10.1002/bimj.201800030
- Menezes, A. F. B., Mazucheli, J., & Barco, K. V. P. (2018). The power inverse Lindley distribution: Different methods of estimation. Ciência e Natura, 40(e24), 1–12. doi:10.5902/2179460X27500
- Menezes, A. F. B., Mazucheli, J., & Dey, S. (2018). The unit-logistic distribution: Different methods of estimation. *Pesquisa Operacional*, 38, 555–578. doi:10.1590/0101-7438.2018.038.03.0555
- Félix, V. B., & Menezes, A. F. B. (2018). Comparisons of ten corrections methods for t-test in multiple comparisons via monte carlo study. *Electronic Journal of Applied Statistical Analysis*, 11(1), 74–91. doi:10.1285/i20705948v11n1p74
- Mazucheli, J., Menezes, A. F. B., & Dey, S. (2018a). Improved maximum-likelihood estimators for the parameters of the unitgamma distribution. *Communications in Statistics - Theory and Meth*ods, 47(15), 3767–3778. doi:10.1080/03610926.2017.1361993
- Mazucheli, J., Menezes, A. F. B., & Dey, S. (2018b). The unit-Birnbaum-Saunders distribution with applications. *Chilean Journal* of Statistics, 9(1), 47–57.
- Mazucheli, J., Menezes, A. F. B., & Ghitany, M. E. (2018). The unit-weibull distribution and associated inference. *Journal of Applied Probability and Statistics*, 13, 1–22.
- Mazucheli, J., Menezes, A. F. B., & Nadarajah, S. (2017). mle.tools: An R Package for Maximum Likelihood Bias Correction. The R Journal, 9(2), 268–290. doi:10.32614/RJ-2017-055

# POSTER PRESENTATIONS

- 2016 Monte Carlo simulation study for post hoc tests, XIII Statistics Research Week, State University of Maringá.
- 2016 Probabilistic distribution for proportions: A baseball application., XIII Statistics Research Week, State University of Maringá.
- 2015 Cluster analysis for time series of hospitalizations for bronchiolitis in the Regional Health Departments of Paraná. XII Statistics Research Week, State University of Maringá.
- 2015 Proposal for a Semivariance Estimator for Big Data. XII Statistics Research Week, State University of Maringá.